Hello, welcome back, and it's lesson we going to see how to create interrupt for our cheap inputs.
We going to see how to enable, extend or interrupt from Cuba makes and then program it in Cuba to eat.
But before we do this, we have to see how the external interrupts are connected and the microcontroller.
So we already know a while a push button is connected to PC 13.
So we keep that in mind.
We need another document here.
We have a number of documents thus far.
We have the the descriptions and the and the user guide of the Hardware Obstruction Leya Library, which
is the hall.
We also have the the user guide for the new clue into this report.
What we need now is the we need a reference module for the microcontroller itself.
Thus far, we don't have the reference manual for the microcontroller.
We have one for the library, the whole library, and then for the Nuclear Discovery Board.
You might think the documents for the Nuclear Discovery Board is supported.
MICROCONTROLLER No, it just talks about these boards, how they are connected schematic.
Do you have a push button, et cetera?
We need to document that tells us about it registers in the chip itself.
So we're going to go to our best friend, Kyouko to, you know, ask for some help like we did earlier.
So I'll come over here or estimate 32 F one one.
And then the word, oh, search here is reference module
over here.
And this first link here, it's a PDF.
So we can click this.
I'm opening in this new tub.
OK, it's over here and there's the reference point.
I'm going to save that as well.
Click over here and advance on this 32 bit.
OK, we can keep.
OK, I'll change the name.
I don't want to get confused.
ASTM 32 F for one one ref my know that's what I'm going to call this.
OK, we can open this.
No, don't lose for that.
Now I think I should close the browser.
OK, can I open this.
So we want to find out where our interrupt lines up.
So I just come here like I do.
These are reference modules you don't need to read.
I read that.
You just need to know where to find what you're looking for.
So I'll press control an F and then I'll search interrupt.
Right.
And then over here it says interrupts.
Let's see what this first one here could do it for us.
This one.
Let's see.
I just start from the top search interrupt and then.
Oh, it interrupts again.
Let's see how many interrupt we have,
OK.
Interrupt.
And which one we're looking for, one that is called the interrupt controller I.
So extend or interrupt configuration register.
Um, we can use a different word, we can use SDI for external interrupt, and I know this stuff because
of experience, right?
So I know what to search for actually.
OK, we have it over here.
External interrupts Event Controller Page 201 or double click this over here.
And it talks about the external interrupt.
It talks about the address.
And then it brings us to this table, this very important table.
Right.
I'm going to zoom in.
So this one tells us external interrupts slash event G.P.A. Krupin.
So over here, it's telling us that all things zero are connected to external interrupts you over here.
It's written etext zero.
So peninsula of every port, whether it's A, B, C, D, E or H, you use external interrupts zero
and then open one external interrupt one all the way to fifteen.
So from this we can tell that our button should be connected to external interruptive.
Uh, thirteen since it is connected to PC thirteen.
So this is what we came for.
Right.
I'm going to minimize this now.
We can go to our estimate 32 QNX to set this up.
I'm going to select my board, it's the new clipboard.
And I'm going to open out come over here.
Claire Penult, I started from scratch because it would take some time for you to get used to it.
That's why I didn't start in the middle.
So let's initialize the normal stuff.
The Cool Stuff System Call says over here, a single wire passes over here.
I'm just going to say bypass for the high speed clock, low speed accident or C, use this ceramic resonator.
And then what we're going to do is our PC 13 or is it.
PG 13 is over here.
I'm going to right click this time rather than choose input.
I'm going to choose keepa.
You extend or interrupt because I want to use interrupt and then we know our lead is five.
So I'll come over here then.
This is the output and we can rename this.
Right, click and to use a label of call this lady.
And then over here, right, click until you saw label BTN
like this.
OK, OK.
Next we need to go to the configuration top to select our interrupter line.
So there's an extra step involved in this one.
That is why it's essential that we do it.
Um, so I'll come over here to.
Systems view over here and then the Enviga over here.
This should open a system for you and Vic.
Right.
So what we want is external interrupt line 13, but we see that cube mix allows us to select this for
interrupt ranging from 10 to 15.
So our 13 falls within this range.
So we take this.
So there's no dedicated Etext I line 13.
There is a dedicated line for interrupt of 10 to 15.
So we take this, OK, once that is done under Enviga, we can go to our project and then give it a
name.
We can call this input interrupt.
And then we can select our two Jane Q idee and then we can generate the project.
Oh, click open project to open it so the project is done opening this old project from our workspace.
So I'll close this and then.
This is all new one input interrupt, so come over here, open source, and then I'll just do a bit
of cleanup.
I'll clean up by reducing the number of comment.
So this is what it looks like after taking up the comment.
Right.
This our main function.
So, OK, um, we going to we saw the init function, the key player in its function already.
So what are we going to do this time is let's the the interrupt turn on the LCD.
To do this, we have to take a look at the function that allows us to deal with interrupt.
We can find this in our While Drive manual, the document we downloaded earlier.
Right.
So if we don't want to always go back to the, um, the dereference manual, one way of doing this,
one way of knowing all the functions available to a particular Peverel is to open the implementation
file of the peripheral so you can come to drive us over here, drive us.
And then this one, SDM three to four hold driver and then we are dealing with GPU.
So you select the whole underscore GPL, you don't see fault double click to open it and you can either
go through the entire driver file or you can come over here and take a look at the outline, the outline
here, its list, the number of defines and the number of functions defined in this file over here.
These are the defined statement, GPL, your mode, etc. These are the functions we have.
GPL you in it, D in it, repin right beento Gilpin in and then we have exten or interrupt your Q handler
over here and then we have the extend or interrupt callback.
So we know these two functions.
Deal with interrupt so we can take a look at the Iraqi handler.
You can just double click this and then it will bring it over here for you.
And then he says this function handles extend or interrupt request.
Krupin specifies the pins connected to it, extend or interrupt line, and then it returns none.
So we can just pass the pin here for the external interrupt and then this will deal with it.
Another way is to use this one here.
The extend or interrupt callback.
It says open specifies the pin connected.
We can use this callback function.
The callback function basically allows us to add our execution in this function.
If you want to perform a computation, if you have got an algorithm that needs to compute when to interrupt,
OK, as you put it in this function such that whenever the interrupt occurs, this function is executed.
And the reason we see this week keyword here is that it means this function can appear twice.
You know, we cannot pick up appear multiple times in a while, you know, our project, whenever we
see week, whenever there is a situation where we have this function defined twice with one starting
with wheat and the other one not having a week and just having this part of it, the one starting with
week is not going to be comp. It's not going to be run, I should say.
So this allows us to be able to copy this function, paste it in our mandatory file and then delete
the week keyword there and then write our own version of it while keeping this where it is without cleaning
it.
Because what happens is often when you have two identical functions in your project, the compiler is
going to complain and tell you you've got multiple definitions of the function.
But if you put a week before the ones you don't need so that you just delete the week keyword when you
need a particular version, then you can get away with it.
So I'm going to copy this over here.
Control.
Easy to copy.
I'll come to amend or C fall.
I can put it anywhere I want.
I can put it above you or let me put it right beneath the main function.
I'll come over here and we can read what it says.
This function should not be modified when the callback is needed.
The whole GPL you extend or Kobuk could be implemented in the use of all this or use of it.
So we want this to execute.
So we delete the week here and then we can just take the note.
We've read it.
So what we want to do is OK, when the interrupt.
OK, here's when what interrupt.
Which is connected to our input case.
What we want to do, we want to do something when I do something over here.
Right.
And remember the interrupted OK, when we press our button basically that is why we connected it to
the push-Button extend or interrupt.
OK, so what we want to do is talk about the ability.
So we'll do so together.
We use the whole
Jhpiego
underscore toggle pin
and then the first argument is going to be the the part which is really the GPL, your port.
And then the second argument is going to be the which is early dippin like this.
Right.
So what is going to happen is we talk about this whenever the interrupt.
OK, so there's nothing else we need to do.
We don't need to write anything in the main function.
This is the beauty of this.
So you can think of this as a background threat, something in the background that is just triggered
whenever there's an interrupt.
And this type, this interrupt is triggered by pressing the push button in our case and this particular
example.
So this is it, right?
So I'm going to build I'm going to click over here to build.
We've got three errors, it could be from our implementation of the early DGP report, so I probably
messed up the the name of the lady was caught early DGP report.
This is correct.
Let's copy the exact same word.
OK, the port shouldn't be capital letters, just start with a capital letter about the Pinelli dependence
should be fined hubo how the hell you togo?
Let's confirm how G.P.A. Togo paid back in the GPL.
You don't see far.
I'm going to check the outline and see what the function is like that how the GPL you told Gilpin's
it takes cheapie you.
Right.
OK.
Looks good, I'll come over here.
Click here to build.
I should close this, it's built successfully and then we can run this click over here, so like this
is 32.
We're going to keep everything the same say, OK.
So this expression, live expression is from our previous project.
OK, I can just close this, dropped this away a bit and then we can click here to run the code, currently
the lead is off when I press, as you can see, when my hand is pressing the LCD on, this means the
interrupters or Keryn.
When I left my hand, it goes off to when I press the interrupt.
OK, yes.
And what we find in the interrupt service routine is executed.
So this is it.
This or there is for this project.
If you have any questions at all, just let me know.
And if you find in the course use for take some time off to leave a review and I'll see you in the next
lesson.
Have a nice day.
Bye bye.
So as you can see, when I press the toggle, look at what is in the interrupt service routine is executed.
So sometimes when I press it sort of stays on because of something known as the bounce.
The the when you are working in embedded systems and you are dealing with push buttons, you've got
to account for depos, because when you press a button rather than the press or caring, once it occurs
multiple times, so often you've got to put a time there.
Some people often implement deboned use in time.
So the really the the Dippin for a number of milliseconds and then read it again to make sure there's
the actual state.
So the reason why you might see some jitter is because we've not, you know, put a system in place
to prevent the bounce.
So there is multiple reading of the same press cos I'm I think I'm pressing just once, but because
it's so fast, the one time press becomes ten times press.
If we were to count and if we were to view the number of times the button is pressed, you realise that
what I would consider a one time press could be 10 or 20 times in the reading of the PIN.
In a way, if you don't understand all of this, you need no worry about that.
I'll see you later.